{"tossups": [{"question": "This empire\u2019s naval commanders included the native Dutchman Jan Janszoon. In the 18th century, this empire\u2019s capital was briefly taken over by the sailor Patrona Halil. This empire\u2019s other naval commanders included Dragut, who served as a galley slave after this empire lost a pivotal battle. This empire\u2019s most famous admiral was Hayrettin Barbarossa, and this empire\u2019s fleet was defeated at the Battle of Navarino during its failed attempt to hold some of its territory. For the point, name this Islamic empire from which Greece won its independence.", "answer": "<b> Ottoman</b> Empire", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist derided James Jeans for not accepting that a certain value was nonzero. This scientist\u2019s son Erwin was hanged for participating in the July 20 Plot to kill Adolf Hitler. Although this man signed the \u201cManifesto of the 93 Intellectuals,\u201d he later rescinded his agreement with sections of it following discussions with Hendrik Lorentz. This man\u2019s namesake law of blackbody radiation solved the \u201cultraviolet catastrophe.\u201d For the point, name this quantum physicist whose namesake constant is represented with a lowercase h.", "answer": "Max<b> Planck</b>", "metadata": "Science - Physics"}, {"question": "This man rebuked a magistrate by saying, \u201cyou are not addressing a third-class pleader.\u201d This man\u2019s fame in law began with the Caucus Case and a successful defense of Bal Gangadhar Tilak from sedition charges. Reforms in the North West Frontier Province and Balochistan were part of this politician\u2019s 1929 presentation of Fourteen Points. The Lahore Resolution, demanding a separate nation, was passed under this man\u2019s leadership. Liaquat Ali Khan served as prime minister with, for the point, what leader of the Muslim League and founder of Pakistan?", "answer": "Muhammad Ali<b> Jinnah</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Lintel construction was used by this civilization to build a gate featuring a pillar that separates two lions. Archaeologists study this civilization at sites like the megaron of Tiryns. Limestone half-columns adorned the portal of a \u201ctholos\u201d tomb built during this civilization that may have belonged to Atreus. Michael Ventris discovered a script used to write this civilization\u2019s language called Linear B. The Mask of Agamemnon was created during, for the point, what Bronze Age Greek civilization that succeeded the Minoans?", "answer": "<b> Mycenae</b>an Greece", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This composer quoted the 10th-century hymn \u201cLord have mercy on us\u201d in an oratorio about the title Christian duchess. This composer of<em> Saint Ludmila</em> was commissioned by Jeanette Thurber to write a <em>Te Deum</em> [tay day-oom] to celebrate the 400th anniversary of America\u2019s discovery. This man was taught African-American spirituals by Harry Burleigh and wrote a symphony whose second movement opens with a English horn solo and was inspired by Longfellow\u2019s<em> Song of Hiawatha</em>. For the point, name this Czech composer who subtitled his<em> Symphony no. 9</em> in D minor \u201cFrom the New World.\u201d", "answer": "Antonin<b> Dvorak</b> ([d\u2019vor-zhak], but be lenient)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "In legend, this natural feature was created by a battle between the sky god Skell and the god of the underworld, Llao. John Wesley Hillman was the first non-Native man to see this feature, which was used in Klamath vision quests. The Phantom Ship and Wizard Island are found in this body of water, as is a tree stump named Old Man of the Lake that has been bobbing in its waters since at least 1896. For the point, name this caldera lake that formed several thousand years ago from the eruption of Mount Mazama in Oregon, the deepest lake in the US.", "answer": "<b> Crater</b> Lake", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "One side in this conflict was colonized via the Condominium Agreement. Emin Pasha was rescued by Henry Morton Stanley during this conflict, in which Menelik II was proclaimed emperor after an invasion of Ethiopia ended in Yohannes IV\u2019s death at Gallabat. The Hadendoa people, who fought under Osman Digna, were nicknamed the \u201cFuzzy Wuzzys\u201d during this war. Shortly after the Fashoda Incident during this conflict, Lord Kitchener wiped out the losing side at Omdurman. For the point, name this war started by a Sudanese self-proclaimed Islamic redeemer.", "answer": "<b> Mahdi</b>st War (or<b> Mahdi</b>st Uprising; accept<b> Anglo-Sudan</b> War; prompt on Sudan Campaign or War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During this campaign, the phrase \u201cWashing Machine Charlie\u201d was used to indicate planes carrying out nighttime attacks. Alexander Patch was the U.S. Army commander in this campaign, during which four Allied cruisers were sunk during an engagement at Savo Island. Henderson Field was a key objective during this battle, which was codenamed Operation Watchtower. This six-month-long battle began in August 1942 after Marines landed on a namesake island and the nearby Tulagi. For the point, name this World War II campaign that took place in the Solomon Islands.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Guadalcanal</b> (or<b> Guadalcanal</b> Campaign, etc.; accept Operation<b> Watchtower </b>before mentioned; prompt on general answers like (the Pacific Theater of) World War II)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this decade, Josef Bachmann shot a prominent figure who coined the phrase \u201clong march through the institutions\u201d as a strategy, Rudi Dutschke. The death of Benno Ohnesorg during this decade sparked a backlash against Kurt Kiesinger, who served as chancellor during the later half of this decade. The SDS, or Socialist German Student Union, arose as a movement during this decade, in which Willy Brandt began his term as chancellor. For the point, name this decade in which a resurgence of Marxism and student activism in West Germany mirrored the rise of the counterculture in the US.", "answer": "19<b>60\u2019s</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this event, Henry Wilson cleared his name by showing he had returned his wife\u2019s shareholdings. This event was brought to light when Henry McComb leaked incriminating letters to the<em> Sun</em> newspaper. Schuyler Colfax was axed as a vice presidential nominee as a result of this event, which centered on Oakes Ames\u2019 bribes to Congressmen and other officials. For the point, name this 1867 scandal involving a French-sounding railroad construction company and Ulysses Grant\u2019s administration.", "answer": "<b> Credit Mobilier</b> (of America) scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Fran\u00b8cois Furet and Keith Michael Baker each argue that this man\u2019s writings caused the Terror. This author wrote a novel in which the title character marries Wolmar instead of her tutor Andr\u00b4e Saint-Preux. Another work by this author identifies the human spirit as the source of \u201cperfectibility,\u201d which led to the establishment of society as the origin of inequality. This author of<em> Julie, or the New Helo\u00a8\u0131se</em> determined that individuals can be forced to obey the general will in a book that begins \u201cMan is born free, but is everywhere in chains.\u201d For the point, name this author of<em> The Social Contract</em>.", "answer": "Jean-Jacques<b> Rousseau</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This man, who survived a 1919 air crash at Rome-Centocelle airport, used the alias John Hume Ross in an attempt to join the RAF. While in Dera\u2019a, this man was captured by the Ottomans and sexually abused. The future King Faisal I of Iraq led a campaign with this man that included victory at the Battle of Aqaba. This man recounted his experiences in the Arab Revolt in the work<em> Seven Pillars of Wisdom</em>. For the point, name this British soldier of World War I who fought primarily in the Arabian peninsula.", "answer": "Thomas Edward<b> Lawrence</b> (accept<b> Lawrence</b> of Arabia)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s brother Richard lifted the Great Siege of Gibraltar and defeated the French Navy during the Glorious First of June. This man scaled the cli\u21b5s of Anse-Au-Foulon to provide an avenue for his superior to strike Quebec, and he later executed an amphibious crossing of the Verazzano Narrows to launch a surprise attack at Long Island. Though he won the Battle of Brandywine to capture Philadelphia, his 1778 resignation led to his replacement by Henry Clinton. For the point, name this British general who replaced Thomas Gage after winning the Battle of Bunker Hill.", "answer": "William<b> Howe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The speech that introduced this idea stated that \u201cthe culminating and final war for human liberty has come.\u201d Much of this idea was recommended by a group of intellectuals nicknamed The Inquiry, whose research was spearheaded by Walter Lippmann. This idea included the mandate that international relations be conducted in the public view, as well as the outline of the foundation of the League of Nations. Territorial boundaries in Europe were the subject of more than half of, for the point, what numbered set of resolutions laid out by Woodrow Wilson after World War I?", "answer": "<b> Fourteen Points</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The target of this uprising, who had succeeded Samuel Mathews in his highest post, allegedly bared his breast and called for this event\u2019s leader to shoot him. A \u201cDeclaration of the People\u201d that was issued as part of this uprising complained that \u201cgreat unjust taxes upon the commonality\u201d were levied by William Berkeley, who refused to retaliate against surrounding Native American tribes. For the point, name this 1676 rebellion led by a Virginian colonist, the first rebellion in the American colonies.", "answer": "<b> Bacon</b>\u2019s Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this war, hospital ships collaborated to treat patients in an area known as \u201cRed Cross Box.\u201dA famous photo of a \u201cYomper\u201d in this war was taken after commandos navigated \u201cBomb Alley\u201d to land at San Carlos. One side in this war used Exocet missiles to sink the<em> HMS Sheffield</em> two days after torpedoes sank their cruiser<em> General Belgrano</em>. Within days of the capture of Port Stanley during this war, Leopoldo Galtieri was overthrown and his country began a democratic transition. For the point, name this 1982 war between the U.K. and Argentina over a South Atlantic archipelago.", "answer": "<b> Falkland</b>s War (accept Guerra de las<b> Malvinas</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In Germany, this holiday\u2019s \u201cOld Women Day\u201d features women raiding city hall in commemoration of a 1824 washerwoman revolt and involves the eating of the traditional \u201ckreppel\u201d donut. The \u201cBattle of the Oranges\u201d takes place during this holiday in Ivrea, Italy, as people memorialize a struggle against a tyrant. Bandas and Blocos are examples of the samba schools that prominently parade in the world\u2019s largest celebration of this holiday. For the point, name this Christian festive holiday that occurs before Lent and often features public masquerade parties, the largest of which takes place in Rio de Janeiro.", "answer": "<b> Carnaval</b> (or<b> Carnival</b>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Note: country and year required. During this election, one politician said that \u201crunning through the fields of wheat\u201d was the naughtiest thing she ever did. Paul Nuttall resigned after his party lost over 10 percent of the vote in this election. Despite warning about a \u201ccoalition of chaos\u201d of opposing parties, the winner of this election was forced into a confidence and supply agreement with the Democratic Unionist Party. This election saw a surprise surge in seats for the Labour Party under Jeremy Corbyn. For the point, name this snap election in which Conservative Prime Minister Theresa May lost her parliamentary majority.", "answer": "<b> 2017 U</b>nited<b> K</b>ingdom general election (prompt on partial answers; prompt on answers of England and/or Great Britain)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "An inscription saying \u201cWelcome, profit\u201d is written on a floor in this city, where an erotic depiction of Priapus was plastered over. A \u201csecret cabinet\u201d in Naples preserves some scandalous artifacts from this city, whose Garden of Fugitives contains some bodily remains. This city su\u21b5ered an earthquake seventeen years before an event recorded in letters by Pliny the Younger, whose uncle died in the nearby city of Stabiae. For the point, name this Italian city that was destroyed along with Herculaneum in 79 AD by the eruption of Mount Vesuvius.", "answer": "<b> Pompeii</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man negotiated a cease-fire with General Eulogio Cantillo [can-tee-yoh] to avoid being trapped after the Battle of Las Mercedes. This man\u2019s forces were targeted in Operation Verano in the Sierra Maestra mountains. This man roughly followed Jos\u00b4e Mart\u00b4\u0131\u2019s journey for a voyage made on a yacht called the<em> Granma</em>. In the July 26th Movement, this man attacked Fulgencio Batista\u2019s forces at the Moncada Barracks. Che Guevara assisted, for the point, what revolutionary who ruled communist Cuba for nearly five decades?", "answer": "<b> F</b>idel<b> Castro</b> (prompt on \u201cCastro\u201d)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was originally slated to lead the first<em> Gemini</em> mission. This man piloted the<em> Antares</em>, which was the first craft of its kind to use color telecasting equipment. This man, who hit two golf balls on the moon during the<em> Apollo 14</em> mission, piloted the<em> Freedom Seven</em> on a mission whose primary goal was achieved less than a month prior by the pilot of the<em> Vostok 1</em>, Yuri Gagarin. For the point, name this member of the<em> Mercury</em> Seven, the first American in space.", "answer": "Alan<b> Shepard</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}], "bonuses": []}